Dear venerables, for a long time I felt
that I should keep the eight precepts,
but I didn't. Finding your teachings two
weeks ago pushed me to finally take them
on. I ended a relationship, shaved my
head, put on white clothes, and have
been dedicated to non-delight in sleep
and food. I'm driven by the urgency of
not knowing how much time I have left
and spend my days in reflection. But
something has shifted. My energy has
collapsed into hopelessness and dread. I
often find myself in tears during the
meals and work periods at the monastery
I'm currently visiting, unable to hide
it. The people around me don't seem to
understand, and I'm starting to wonder
if anyone ever could. Now, I see that a
part of myself is yearning to give up
these eight precepts and revert back to
the five. But something in me has
shifted and knows that that path leads
nowhere. I know going back would fix
nothing and yet part of me fears that I
will. How do I endure this?
>> Right? So that's the difference between
you logically understanding what's good
for you and then actually feeling that
that's what's good for you, so to speak,
so that you actually stop wanting the
opposite. And well, the first
thing that you need to get out of the
way is to understand that if you act out
of that feeling that's still there of
uh desire towards what isn't good for
you, then there's no way that that wrong
perception will fade. It will only
become stronger. And it might even come
a point where the strength of that
pressure will
um like take over even your now factual
recognition of what's good for you. So
you have to be clear about the fact that
okay whatever I choose
um I will not be able to remain static.
It's not like I can stay where I am and
sort of resume later. If I choose to go
down that path, I will lose what I have
built up and I might end up even in in
an even worse position.
So you want to be clear about that
because then it it be it that will play
a big part in the in what you choose.
You won't be able to as many people do
maintain the view that you are
practicing while you're actually not
restrained from sensuality. you'll be
clear that actually I have chosen to go
in the opposite direction.
And so um
now in terms of what do you do if you do
choose to uh keep the eight precepts?
Well, you have to recognize to what
extent you're actually responsible for
that um
sense of
gratification and enjoyment of the
things that you've given up that's still
there. You want to realize that actually
you're not doing that anymore.
Like you said, you're you yourself have
a clear line that you're not crossing
because you started keeping your
precepts. And so that's that's arisen on its own.
And so that's that's arisen on its own.
That's not something that you're doing.
In fact, you would probably
not have it be there anymore if you
could help it.
So it's important to see then that
you shouldn't overreach beyond that
point and then try to suppress or or
speed up the abandonment of that
delight. Instead, it's when you leave it
be there, but don't act out of it and
don't try to get rid of it that it will
actually start subsiding
from the very base where it is rather
than simply suppressing it through like
an engagement of you
uh almost like through sense of
willpower doing this and doing that and
and striving and contemplating.
Meanwhile, that thing kind of lingers at
the background and you know that as soon
as you relax and sit down, it's going to
come back and take over. So that's not
the right type of abandonment. The only
right type of abandonment is when even
if you were to not strive anymore, that
desire just isn't there. And the only
way you can achieve that is if you learn
how to
well, as we say, endure it on the right
level. Which means
um it certainly doesn't mean that you
allow the fantasizing and memories and
thoughts that that state will be trying
to push on you. You have to restrain
that but then at the same time you you
try to keep in check that sense of oh
this is that sense of ownership over it
basically sense of uh I have a right to
make this go away on my own terms
you don't in the same way as
you you didn't even ask for that state
in it to begin with it built up as a
result of the stuff that you've been
doing in the past as a as as a kind of
momentum that you have accumulated
through your past actions. So now in the
same way you won't be able to just shift
gears immediately into the other
direction. You have to start building up
that momentum so that then your mind
starts actually delighting in
renunciation and then that's the thing
that's happening on its own rather than
this. And then you will realize in the
same way that now it feels
probably almost impossible
to actually
um not have those unh wholesome
inclinations. Well, if you cultivate the
opposite type of type of momentum, it
will stop feeling impossible to have the
unh wholesome inclinations. It will feel
like the mind is just on its own um
preferring the precepts, preferring
renunciation. And the thought of going
back is inconceivable. So
So
that's the end result of you
seeing that state of mind as arisen and
not interfering with it. As the sadanas
describes, you recognize the mind of
lust as a mind of lust. You don't add on
top of that. And if you are recognizing
it as a mind of lust, you won't be able
to uh proliferate the thoughts it wants
you to proliferate at the same time.
Those are mutually exclusive. So, you
don't have to be afraid that if I don't
uh deal with it as soon as possible that
I'll somehow be falling prey to it. You
can't fall prey to it if you're
recognizing it as an arisen state of
mind at the same time.
>> Can't you recognize it as an arisen
state of mind that you don't like and
want to get rid of?
>> Yeah. But the thing is, if you were to
start trying to get rid of it, you
wouldn't be recognizing it anymore.
So that's also mutually exclusive. Like
you certainly don't want to
uh have a view that it's a good state or
something and that it's okay,
but that doesn't justify because like
factually you will lose perspective over
it if you start trying to get rid of it.
You'll re realize the only way I can
really see it is is if I'm not engaging
with it. It's the same of like u if if
if you're looking at something from a
higher ground, you won't be able to go
and and wrestle with it and keep that
higher ground at the same time. It's
just that it might feel unpleasant to
have to look at it. But you have to
realize, well, as long as I don't go
down there where it is, I'm not gonna
get injured. There's no way. It can't
like somehow magically hit me from afar.
It's only when I go and start for
whatever reason get close to it. That's
when I get in trouble. And it will take
time to full for that to fully sink in
because everything that you've lived so
far is about inter like immediately
jumping into your states of mind in
whichever direction to get rid of them
or to to manipulate them out of that
sense of ownership that you still have.
And yeah, the sense of giving up the
sense of ownership doesn't mean that you
you your mind kind of ends up
uh neglected because it's not yours
anymore. It's actually the opposite. If
you cultivate non ownership, your mind
will be purified as a result. But that's
not something you can do out of a sense
of ownership. You can't take your
ownership for granted and then use it to
try to purify your mind.
Ownership is what pollutes the mind.